<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
  <section id="check_ycp_quickstart">
    <title>Quick Start</title>
    <para>
      Simply invoke <literal>check_ycp</literal> with the YCP file(s) you wish to check as
      arguments:
      <screen>
check_ycp <emphasis>myfile.ycp</emphasis>
      </screen>

      <screen>
check_ycp *.ycp
      </screen>

    </para>
    <para>
      The error messages should be self explanatory. They stick to the GNU standards
      for error messages, so you can use your favourite editor's
      (e.g. <link linkend="check_ycp_emacs">Emacs</link>)
	function to process them.
    </para>

    <para>
      Most of the checks can individually be turned off.
      Type
      <screen>
check_ycp -h
      </screen>

      for a complete list of command line options. Those options are intentionally
      not listed here since such a list would inevitably be outdated before too long.
    </para>


  </section>



  <section id="check_ycp_why">
    <title>Why this Document?</title>

    <para>
      Even though using <literal>check_ycp</literal> is pretty straightforward, some background
      information is useful in order to understand what it does, its output and the
      limitations of this tool - in short, what you can expect it to do and why not
      to blindly rely on it.
    </para>

    <para>
      <literal>check_ycp</literal> is far from fool proof. In fact, it is pretty dumb. It just
      tries to parse YCP code ("try" is the operative word here!) and applies various
      checks for obvious programming errors. Some errors it will catch and report,
      many it will not. But we (i.e. the YaST2 core development team) decided we'd
      rather have a tool with limited capabilities than none at all.
    </para>

    <para>
      Another reason for writing this document is pointing out why we try to enforce
      certain things, many of which are because of ergonomics or mere conventions in
      developing as a team, not true requirements of YaST2 or the YCP language.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="check_ycp_header_comments">
    <title>Header Comment Checks</title>

    <para>
      The YaST2 team uses a standardized file header format for YCP modules.
      Standard fields are included there for various purposes - see the "why"
      sections of the individual checks.
    </para>

    <para>
      Everything up to the first opening brace "<literal>{</literal>" outside a comment is
      considered part of the header. Nothing outside this portion of the file is
      checked. You may, however, open and close as many comments as you like up to
      this opening brace.
    </para>

    <para>
      Leading asterisks "<literal>*</literal>" at the start of lines are silently discarded
      since they are often used to beautify multi line comments.
    </para>

    <para>
      The comment markers themselves of course are also discarded for the checks:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><literal>   /*</literal></listitem>
	<listitem><literal>   */</literal></listitem>
	<listitem><literal>   //</literal></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="check_ycp_filename">
    <title>Filename Check</title>

    <simplesect>
      <title>What</title>
      <para>
	If present, the contents of a <literal>Module</literal> field is checked against the
	current file name.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Why</title>

      <para>
	Much code gets written by copying existing code. There is nothing wrong with
	that (in fact, it saves a lot of work), but when you do, please change fields
	accordingly - fields like <literal>Author</literal>, <literal>Maintainer</literal>,
	<literal>Purpose</literal> etc. - and the file name in <literal>Module</literal>.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>How</title>

      <para>
	This file name is particularly easy to check (plus, it's the only one that can
	reliably be checked), so <literal>check_ycp</literal> checks it: It compares the base
	name (not the complete path) of the current file to what you specified in
	<literal>Module:</literal> in the header.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Author / Maintainer Entry Check</title>

    <simplesect><title>What</title>
      <para>
	<literal>check_ycp</literal> checks the file header for presence of at least one of
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><literal>Author:</literal></listitem>
	  <listitem><literal>Authors:</literal></listitem>
	  <listitem><literal>Maintainer:</literal></listitem>
	  <listitem><literal>Maintainers:</literal></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	If found, each entry is checked for some contents, i.e. it may not be
	completely empty (but use whitespace as you like).
      </para>

      <para>
	The contents must include something that looks like an e-mail address.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Why</title>

      <para>
	There must be at least one person to contact when there are any problems or
	questions about the module. The full name is desired, but at least an e-mail
	address must be there to get in contact with the maintainer or the author.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>How</title>

      <para>
	The fields are checked for presence of something like
	<literal>somebody@somewhere.domain</literal> - in fact only for something before the at
	sign "@" and something with a period "." behind it.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>CVS Id: Marker Check</title>

    <simplesect><title>What</title>

      <para>
	Presence of a Id CVS / RCS identity marker is checked, e.g.
	<screen>
            Id myfile.ycp,v 1.2 2001/02/14 18:04:50 sh Exp 
	</screen>
      </para>


    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Why</title>

      <para>
	This CVS / RCS ID is the only way of finding out exactly what CVS revision the
	file has and what change date. The file date (what <literal>ls -l</literal> shows) is
	absolutely unreliable and irrelevant: This may have changed just by copying the
	file around which didn't change anything.
      </para>

      <para>
	This is important for bug tracking and for finding and fixing bugs - only when
	a developer knows what version of a file has been used he has a chance to
	reproduce a bug - or even make sure that a supposedly fixed bug didn't turn up
	again.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>How</title>

      <para>
	Presence of
	<screen>
Id:
	</screen>

	is checked. There may be more characters before the closing dollar sign
	"<literal>$</literal>", but the exact contents is not checked.
      </para>


      <note>
	<para>
	  When creating a new file, it is absolutely sufficient to
	  include the unexpanded string ("<literal>Id:</literal>") somewhere in the
	  file. CVS or RCS will automatically expand this to the full ID string.

	</para>
      </note>

    </simplesect>
  </section>



  <section>
    <title>Translatable Messages Checks</title>

    <section>
      <title><literal>textdomain</literal> Check</title>

      <simplesect>
	<title>What</title>

	<para>
	  If there is any message that is marked for translation with
	  <literal>_("</literal>...<literal>")</literal>, there must be a <literal>textdomain</literal>
	  statement.
	</para>
      </simplesect>
      <simplesect>
	<title>Why</title>

	<para>
	  The YaST2 translator module needs to know where to take the messages to be
	  translated from. This is what the <literal>textdomain</literal> specification does.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Technically one <literal>textdomain</literal> statement somewhere in the YCP program
	  would be sufficient, i.e. include files or modules called with
	   <literal>CallFunction()</literal> don't really require an
	  additional <literal>textdomain</literal> specification.
	</para>

	<para>
	  However, it is highy recommended all YCP files with translatable messages
	  include their own <literal>textdomain</literal> statement so each YCP file is
	  self-sufficient in that regard, thus more easily reusable for other
	  purposes. This policy is enforced with this check.
	</para>

      </simplesect>
      <simplesect>
	<title>How</title>

	<para>
	  After being stripped of all comments, the entire YCP code is scanned for the
	  translation marker sequence: An underscore immediately followed by an opening
	  parenthesis: <literal>_(</literal>
	</para>

	<para>
	  If this sequence is found, presence of translatable messages is assumed. If no
	  <literal>textdomain</literal> statment is found there will be an error.
	</para>

	<para>
	  On the other hand, if there is no text to translate, a <literal>textdomain</literal>
	  statement is not necessary (but it can't hurt).
	</para>


	<note>
	  <para>
	    Theoretically the "<literal>_(</literal>" sequence contained in a
	    literal string (i.e. within double quotes
            <literal>"</literal>...<literal>"</literal>)
	    could falsely trigger this error, too. But if you do that, you are very likely
	    to run into trouble with other tools as well - most likely even the original
	    <literal>getext</literal> tools regularly used to extract the messages for
	    translation. Bottom line: Don't do that.
	  </para>
	</note>
      </simplesect>
    </section>

</section>
    <section id="check_ycp_html-check">
      <title>RichText / HTML Sanity Check</title>

      <para>
	Literal strings in YCP code that contains HTML tags are usually help text that
	will be displayed in the YaST2 RichText widget. This HTML text is subjected to
	the sanity checks explained below.
      </para>

      <para>
	Please notice that everything within double quotes <literal>"</literal> will be
	checked that contains anything surrounded by angle brackets
	<literal>&lt;</literal>...<literal>&gt;</literal> - i.e. anything that looks remotely like an HTML
	tag. Unknown tags will be silently ignored, but the entire text within the
	quotes will be checked.
      </para>

      <formalpara><title>Limitation:</title>
	<para>
	  If a portion of help text lacks any HTML tag, it will not be checked since it
	  will not be recognized by <literal>check_ycp</literal> as help text. Such completely
	  wrong portions of help text will slip through undetected, thus unchecked.
	</para>
      </formalpara>
    <section>
      <title>Completeness of &lt;p&gt; / &lt;/p&gt; Paragraph Tags</title>

      <simplesect>
	<title>What</title>

	<para>
	  Each HTML text must start with a <literal>&lt;p&gt;</literal> tag and end with a
	  <literal>&lt;/p&gt;</literal> tag.
	</para>

	<para>
	  There must be a corresponding closing <literal>&lt;/p&gt;</literal> tag for each opening
	  <literal>&lt;p&gt;</literal> tag.
	</para>

      </simplesect>
      <simplesect><title>Why</title>

	<para>
	  This is a basic requirement of HTML. The underlying YaST2 widgets may or may
	  not be forgiving enough to tolerate missing tags, but we'd rather not rely on
	  that.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Besides, no other types of paragraphs other than plain text paragraphs
	  <literal>&lt;</literal>p<literal>&gt;</literal> ... <literal>&lt;</literal>/p<literal>&gt;</literal> are desired in
	  YaST2 help texts - in particular, no large font boldface headings etc.
	</para>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect><title>How</title>
	<para>
            See the <link linkend="check_ycp_html-check">intro</link> of this section.
	</para>
      </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Text Before, After, Between Paragraphs</title>

      <simplesect><title>What</title>

	<para>
	  For each portion of HTML text:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>No text before the first <literal>&lt;p&gt;</literal> tag is
	      permitted.</listitem>

	    <listitem>No text after the last <literal>&lt;/p&gt;</literal> tag is
	      permitted.</listitem>

	    <listitem>No text between a closing <literal>&lt;/p&gt;</literal> and the next opening
	      <literal>&lt;p&gt;</literal> tag is permitted.</listitem>

	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

      </simplesect>
      <simplesect><title>Why</title>
	<para>
	  Each of those cases is a simple yet common HTML syntax error.
	</para>

      </simplesect>
      <simplesect><title>How</title>
	<para>
            See the <link linkend="check_ycp_html-check">intro</link> of this section.
	</para>
      </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section><title>No More Than One Paragraph per Message</title>

      <simplesect><title>What</title>
	<para>
	  Each single portion of HTML text may contain exactly one paragraph, i.e. one
	  <literal>&lt;</literal>p<literal>&gt;</literal> ... <literal>&lt;</literal>/p<literal>&gt;</literal>
	  pair.
	</para>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect><title>Why</title>
	<para>
	  This is a convention to make life easier for the translators.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The tools used for extracting translatable texts from the sources (GNU
	  <literal>gettext</literal>) detect differences between the last translated version of a
	  message and the current message from the latest source. They mark such messages
	  as <emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis>, i.e. the (human) translator is asked to have a good look at
	  it and decide whether there has been a real change in the message (thus it
	  needs to be retranslated) or just a cosmetic change (fixed typo, inserted
	  whitespace, reformatted the paragraph etc.).
	</para>

	<para>
	  This is a tedious task and it gets more tedious the longer each individual
	  portion of text becomes. Changes from the old to the new version are hard to
	  find if the portions are very long.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Plus, if they are that long it is very likely that always somewhere something
	  has changed, thus the entire text is marked as <emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis> and needs
	  careful manual checking which is not really necessary for all the text.
	</para>
      </simplesect>
      <simplesect>
          <title>Workaround</title>

      <para>
	Split your help texts and use the YCP string addition operator to put them
	together.
      </para>

      <formalpara>
	<title>Don't:</title>

        <para>
	  <screen>
help_text = _("&lt;p&gt;
bla blurb bla ...
blurb bla blurb ...
bla blurb bla ...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
bla blurb bla ...
blurb bla blurb ...
bla blurb bla ...
&lt;/p&gt;");
	  </screen>
	</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara>
	<title>Instead, do:</title>
	<para>
	  <screen>
// Help text (HTML like)
help_text = _("&lt;p&gt;
bla blurb bla ...
blurb bla blurb ...
bla blurb bla ...
&lt;/p&gt;");

// Help text (HTML like), continued
help_text = help_text + _("&lt;p&gt;
bla blurb bla ...
blurb bla blurb ...
bla blurb bla ...
&lt;/p&gt;");
	  </screen>
	</para>
      </formalpara>

      <para>
	Please also notice the <emphasis>comments</emphasis> for the translators just above the
	text. The <literal>gettext</literal> tools will automatically extract them along with the
	text to translate and put them into the <literal>.po</literal> file. The translators can
	use them as additional hints what this text is all about.
      </para>
    </simplesect>


    <simplesect><title>How</title>
      <para>
          See the <link linkend="check_ycp_html-check">intro</link> of this section.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Excess Forced Line Breaks &lt;br&gt; after Paragraphs</title>

      <simplesect><title>What</title>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Forced line break</emphasis> tags <literal>&lt;br&gt;</literal> are discouraged, especially
	  after a paragraph end tag <literal>&lt;/p&gt;</literal>.
	</para>
      </simplesect>
      <simplesect><title>Why</title>
	<para>
	  Such forced line breaks are plain superfluous. The HTML renderer will format
	  the paragraph automatically - after each paragraph there will be a newline and
	  some empty space to set each paragraph apart from the next.
	</para>

	<para>
	  There is no need nor is it desired to add extra empty space between
	  paragraphs. This just looks plain ugly, even more so if this results in
	  different spacings between several paragraphs of the same help text.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The most superfluous of those excess line breaks are those at the very end of a
	  help text - after the last paragraph. Not only are they not good for anything,
	  they sometimes even cause a vertical scroll bar to be displayed even though
	  this would not be necessary otherwise.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Plus, there have been cases where erstwhile last help text paragraphs had been
	  rearranged so they now are in the middle of the help text - but unfortunately
	  the trailing <literal>&lt;br&gt;</literal> tag had been forgotten and moved along with
	  the paragraph, thus causing different inter-paragraph spacings.
	</para>

	<para>
	  To make things even worse, fixing this breaks the translation for the affected
	  paragraph: It will be marked as <emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis> just because of this even though
	  it has not really changed.
	</para>

	<para>
	  We cannot entirely get rid of the <literal>&lt;br&gt;</literal> tags (but we would like
	  to). Sometimes they are needed <emphasis>within</emphasis> paragraphs. But at least those
	  at the end of paragraphs we can do without.
	</para>
      </simplesect>
      <simplesect><title>How</title>
	<para>
	  <literal>&lt;br&gt;</literal> after <literal>&lt;/p&gt;</literal> (maybe with anything in
	  between) is rejected. All other <literal>&lt;br&gt;</literal> tags are silently ignored.
	</para>

      </simplesect>

  </section>
    </section>
  <section id="check_ycp_widget-checks"><title>Widget / UI Function Parameter Checks</title>

    <para>
      Parameters to YaST2 UI widgets plus some commonly used functions
      (e.g. <literal>Wizard::SetContents()</literal>, <literal>Popup::Message()</literal> etc.) are checked
      where possible - if the parameters are simple string constants, maybe
      surrounded by translation markers ("<literal>_("</literal>...<literal>")</literal>").
    </para>

    <para>
      Optional widget parameters like <literal>`opt(...)</literal> or <literal>`id(...)</literal> are
      ignored.
    </para>

    <para>
      The following examples <emphasis>will be checked:</emphasis>

      <programlisting>
PushButton("OK");
      </programlisting>
      <programlisting>
PushButton( _("Cancel"));
      </programlisting>
      <programlisting>
PushButton(`id(`apply), _("Apply"));
      </programlisting>
      <programlisting>
PushButton(`opt(`default), _("OK"));
      </programlisting>

    </para>

    <para>
      More complex parameters like variable contents or YCP terms cannot be checked.
    </para>

    <para>
      The parser used in <literal>check_ycp</literal> for that is really dumb. In fact, it only
      scans for keywords like <literal>PushButton</literal> outside string constants, tries to
      find the corresponding matching pair of parentheses "<literal>(</literal>...<literal>)</literal>"
      and splits everything inside into comma-separated subexpressions.
    </para>

    <para>
      Only the most basic of those subexpressions are checked - only simple string
      constants <literal>"</literal>...<literal>"</literal> or string constants marked for
      translation <literal>_("</literal>...<literal>")</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The following examples <emphasis>will not be checked:</emphasis>

      <programlisting>CheckBox( "/dev/"+device );</programlisting>
      <programlisting>CheckBox( sformat("/dev/%1"), device );</programlisting>
      <programlisting>CheckBox( GetDevName() );</programlisting>
      <programlisting>
	string message = "OK";
	PushButton( message );
    </programlisting>
    </para>

  <section id="check_ycp_widget-shortcut">
    <title>Keyboard Shortcut Check</title>

    <simplesect><title>What</title>

      <para>
	Widgets that can have a keyboard shortcut (one character marked with an
	ampersand "<literal>&amp;</literal>") are checked for presence of a keyboard shortcut.
      </para>

      <note>
	<para>
	  Consistency of the keyboard shortcuts is <emphasis>not</emphasis> checked,
	  only presence. <literal>check_ycp</literal> cannot know which widgets will be on-screen
	  at the same time, thus it cannot find out whether the same keyboard shortcut
	  has been assigned twice to different widgets.
	</para>
      </note>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Why</title>

      <para>
	This is for users whose mouse doesn't work (especially during installation
	time) as well as for experienced users who prefer working with the
	keyboard. Navigation from one widget to another is much easier when each widget
	that can get the keyboard focus can be reached with an <emphasis>[Alt]</emphasis> key
	sequence rather than repeatedly using the <emphasis>[Tab]</emphasis> key and/or the cursor
	keys.
      </para>

      <para>
	There may be a lot more widgets that can have keyboard shortcuts than you
	expected. Basically, every widget that can somehow be operated with the
	keyboard (even if it is only scrolling) and that has an associated label
	(within, above or beside) can have a keyboard shortcut and should get one.
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect><title>How</title>

      <para>
	The widget parameter that acts as a label is checked for presence of exactly
	one ampersand "<literal>&amp;</literal>".
      </para>
      <para>
          See the <link linkend="check_ycp_widget-checks">widget checks</link> of this section for more.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
  </section>
  <section id="check_ycp_widget-trans">
    <title>Translatable Messages Check</title>

    <simplesect><title>What</title>

      <para>
	Widget parameters that are displayed literally as text are checked for
	translation markers ("<literal>_("</literal>...<literal>")</literal>").
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect><title>Why</title>

      <para>
	Every text message that ever gets to the end user is to be translated into the
	user's native language. This can only be made sure if the message is marked for
	translation.
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect><title>How</title>
      <para>
          See the <link linkend="check_ycp_widget-checks">intro</link> of this section.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section><title>Standardized Lib Function Checks</title>
    <!--
    <para>TODO update this WRT Label and Popup. mvidner</para>
    <para>TODO document the import checking. mvidner</para>
    -->

    <section><title>Duplicate Definitions of Wizard Lib Functions</title>

      <simplesect><title>What</title>

	<para>
	  Presence of definitions of functions from the <emphasis>wizard lib</emphasis> (Package
	  <literal>yast2</literal>) outside the <emphasis>wizard library</emphasis> itself is checked
	  such as <literal>Wizard::SetContents()</literal> etc.
	</para>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect><title>Why</title>

	<para>
	  At the start of YaST2 develompent there was no other way of sharing code other
	  than simply copying it. Those days are gone; YCP now supports an
	  <literal>include</literal> mechanism similar to C or C++.
	</para>
      <para>
	Very general code like how to create the typical YaST2 wizard window layout has
	now been moved to the <emphasis>wizard lib</emphasis>, a collection of include files that
	provide such facilities. We want to get rid of duplicate code as soon as
	possible for obvious reasons (consistency, maintainability, efficiency).
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect><title>How</title>

      <para>
	If "<literal>define</literal>" followed by one of the known function names of the
	<emphasis>wizard lib</emphasis> is found outside the file where this is supposed to be, a
	warning is issued. Both function names and file names are hardwired within
	<literal>check_ycp</literal>.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
  </section>

  <section><title>Definitions and Usage of Obsolete Functions</title>

    <simplesect><title>What</title>

      <para>
	Usage or presence of definitions of known obsolete functions is checked,
	e.g. <literal>Popup::Message()</literal>, <literal>Popup::YesOrNo()</literal> etc.; using an equivalent
	replacement function from the <emphasis>wizard lib</emphasis>'s <literal>common_popups.ycp</literal>
	include file is suggested.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
    <simplesect><title>Why</title>

      <para>
	Those functions are now superseded by those from
	<literal>common_popups.ycp</literal>. The replacement functions usually require less
	parameters (thus are easier to use) and use a common and consistent widget
	layout.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect><title>How</title>

      <para>
	The definitions are checked very much like the wizard function definitions
	above; function and file names are hardwired here as well.
      </para>

      <para>
	Usage of the obsolete functions is checked simply by checking for occurrence of
	the function name followed by an opening parenthesis (maybe with whitespace in
	between) somewhere in the code.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
  </section>

  <section><title>Usage of Predefined Messages</title>

    <simplesect><title>What</title>

      <para>
	Presence of predefined message strings is checked, e.g. "<literal>&amp;Next</literal>",
	"<literal>&amp;Back</literal>" etc.; using a corresponding function from the <emphasis>wizard
            lib</emphasis> (<literal>Label</literal> Module) is suggested,
	e.g. <literal>Label::NextButton()</literal>, <literal>Label::BackButton()</literal> etc.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
    <simplesect><title>Why</title>

      <para>
	<itemizedlist>

	  <listitem><para>
	      Ease the burden on the translators - with the predefined messages they don't
	      need to translate the same standard texts over and over again.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      Consistent messages for the same type of buttons etc. throughout all of YaST2.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>


	  <listitem><para>
	      Consistent keyboard shortcuts for the same button throughout all of YaST2.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>


	  <listitem><para>
	      If we ever need to change one of those standard messages, we can do that centralized.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </simplesect>


    <simplesect>
      <title>How</title>

      <para>
	The YCP code, stripped of comments, is checked for any one of the predefined
	messages (including any keyboard shortcuts that may be there), surrounded by
	translation markers ("<literal>_("</literal>...<literal>")</literal>").
      </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>Limitations

      <para>
	Differences in spelling or only in whitespace will not be caught. If there is
	no or another keyboard shortcut, the message will not be considered the same -
	so if anybody uses "<literal>Ne&amp;xt</literal>" rather than "<literal>&amp;Next</literal>", this will go
	undetected.
      </para>

    </simplesect>
  </section>
  </section>


      <section><title>Alternative Variable Declarations</title>

      <simplesect><title>What</title>

	<para>
	  Alternative variable declarations are rejected, e.g.
	  <screen>

string|void value = anything();
symbol|term result = UI::UserInput();
integer|string x = 42;

	  </screen>
	</para>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect>
          <title>Why</title>

	<para>
	  Just about the only situation where this made sense was when a variable might
	  sometimes be <literal>nil</literal> to indicate some error condition. All other variants
	  of this are of purely academic nature or (more likely) poor programming
	  style. Since all YCP types can be <literal>nil</literal> now, however, this feature
	  becomes totally redundant. It will very likely be dropped in the near future.
	</para>
      </simplesect>
      <simplesect>
          <title>How</title>

	<para>
	  The entire YCP code, stripped of comments, is checked for occurences of one of
	  the primitive YCP types (<literal>string</literal>, <literal>integer</literal>, <literal>boolean</literal>,
	  <literal>map</literal>, <literal>list</literal>, <literal>any</literal>, <literal>void</literal> etc.) followed by a
	  pipe sign <literal>|</literal> (maybe with whitespace before or after it) and
	  another primitive YCP type.
	</para>


      </simplesect>
  </section>
      <section><title>Checking YCP Examples</title>

	<para>
	  You probably don't want to perform all of the available checks for simple YCP
	  examples. Those should be concise and written for legibility rather than for
	  completeness. They will usually not contain a standard format file header with
	  all bells and whistles, no translation markers etc. - you don't want to bloat
	  <literal>HelloWorld.ycp</literal> with all that stuff.
	</para>

	<para>
            <literal>check_ycp</literal> has a special <emphasis>example mode</emphasis> for just this purpose: It
	    turns off all checks that don't make sense for simple examples, yet allows you
	    to use <literal>check_ycp</literal> anyway. If you think <emphasis>"well, what's left
	      then?"</emphasis> think about the future. <literal>check_ycp</literal> can and will be expanded
	    to cover more and more checks, and even your examples can benefit from it.
	</para>

	<para>
	  For simple YCP examples (and only for them, please!) invoke <literal>check_ycp</literal> with
	  the <literal>-x</literal> command line option:

	  <screen>
check_ycp -x HelloWorld.ycp
	  </screen>
	</para>

	<para>
	  This turns off all checks that don't make sense for examples.
	</para>

      </section>


  <section id="check_ycp_emacs">
      <title><literal>check_ycp</literal> and Emacs</title>

    <para>
      <literal>check_ycp</literal> and Emacs go together well:

      <itemizedlist>

	<listitem>Load a YCP file into Emacs.</listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Invoke the Emacs compile command:</para>
	    <programlisting>
M-x compile
	    </programlisting>
	  </listitem>

	    <listitem><para>Edit the compile command ("<literal>make -k</literal>" by default) in the
		minibuffer; change it to the <literal>check_ycp</literal> command you wish to invoke (you only need to do this once for each Emacs session):

		<programlisting>
check_ycp *.ycp
		</programlisting>
	      </para>
          </listitem>

	      <listitem>Hit <emphasis>Return</emphasis></listitem>

	      <listitem><para>Use the <literal>next-error</literal> function to go to the next error
		  <literal>check_ycp</literal> has reported. The corresponding YCP file will automatically be
		  loaded into Emacs if needed, and Emacs will jump to the corresponding line
		  within that file.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>


    <para>
      If you haven't done so already, you might want to bind the <literal>compile</literal> and
      <literal>next-error</literal> functions to keys in your <literal>~/.emacs</literal> file, e.g.

      <screen>
(global-set-key "f42" 'compile)
(global-set-key "f43" 'next-error)
      </screen>

    </para>

    <para>
      The real challenge here is to find a key that is not already in use for some
      other important function.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you are a real hardcore YCP hacker, you can even go so far and change the
      default compile command to <literal>check_ycp</literal> in <literal>~/.emacs</literal>:

      <screen>
(setq compile-command "check_ycp *.ycp")
      </screen>

    </para>


  </section>



  <section><title>Extending <literal>check_ycp</literal></title>

      <section><title>Adding new Widgets / UI Functions</title>

      <para>
	Everybody should be able to add checks for a new widget or a new function that
	uses keyboard shortcuts (unlikely) or translatable messages (very likely) -
	even without any knowledge of Perl:
    </para>

	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Locate the <literal>check_widget_params()</literal>
	      function.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Add your widget to the list (the large regexp) near the function beginning,
	      where all the other widgets are. Be careful not to include any whitespace
	      (blanks or tabs) inside the parentheses.
	      <emphasis>Wrong:</emphasis>
	      <programlisting>( MyNewWidget ) |</programlisting>

	      <emphasis>OK:</emphasis>
	      <programlisting>(MyNewWidget) |</programlisting>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Add an <literal>elsif()</literal> branch to the large
	      <literal>if()</literal>...<literal>elsif()</literal>...<literal>elsif()</literal> construction:

	      <programlisting>
elsif ( $widget =~ /MyWidget/ )
{
    check_keyboard_shortcut ( $widget, $line_no, 1, @args );
    check_translation       ( $widget, $line_no, 1, @args );
}
	      </programlisting>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>

      <para>
	You might have to change the third parameter according to your widget or
	function: This is the number of the parameter to be checked (the first one is
	1) after all <literal>`opt()</literal> and <literal>`id()</literal> parameters have been removed.
      </para>

      <para>
          Of course you can omit the <link linkend="check_ycp_widget-shortcut">keyboard
              shortcut check</link>
	   (<literal>check_keyboard_shortcut()</literal>) if it doesn't make sense for your
	  widget or function.
      </para>

      <para>
          If there is more than one parameter to be <link linkend="check_ycp_widget-trans">checked for translatable messages</link>, add a call to <literal>check_translation()</literal> for
	  each.
      </para>
    </section>


    <section><title>Other Extensions</title>

      <para>
	Like Linus Torvalds once said: <emphasis>"Use the source, Luke!"</emphasis> ;-)
      </para>

      <para>
	<literal>check_ycp</literal>'s sources are extensively commented, even the many regular
	expressions used there. But changing those regexps really requires some
	in-depth knowledge of regexps in general and Perl regexps in particular. If you
	feel unsafe, better not touch them.
      </para>

      <para>
	Other than that, use your creativity.
      </para>


    </section>
  </section>
